Rachel Williams

CONTACT

Seattle, Washington

E-mail: williamsrachelada@gmail.com

Website: https://github.com/racheladaw, https://dev.to/racheladaw,

Phone: 954-257-3114

SUMMARY

Full-stack **Software Engineer** experienced in designing and building single page web applications. My primary languages and frameworks are Ruby, Rails, JavaScript, React, and SQL. Previously a senior manufacturing specialist with five years in the Biotechnology industry, I know how to work with a team to efficiently execute and troubleshoot complex processes. I pride myself in my ability to solve difficult problems and communicate effectively with emotional intelligence.

SOFTWARE

Ruby: Rails, Rails API, ActiveRecord, Sinatra

Javascript: React, Redux, Thunk, JQuery, AJAX

HTML, CSS, SQL(SQLite3, PostgreSQL), Git, REST, Bootstrap, JSON, APIs

PROJECTS

Concert Buddy - Github Front-End: http://bit.ly/2GawuD6 / Back-End: http://bit.ly/2v30kal | Demo: http://bit.ly/2tCAKIT

A single page web application using a **React** / **Redux** front-end and a **Rails API** backend that allows you to view upcoming concerts in your area and save the ones you would like to attend.

- Utilized RestClient gem to acquire concert data from SeatGeek'sAPI based on a user's location
- Used **Thunk** middleware and lifecycle methods to make asynchronous requests in action creator functions
- Integrated Redux to manage state including details about current user and data about concerts in their area
- Employed React Router to create RESTful routes to inform the user of their location within the app
- Incorporated sessions and bcrypt gem in Rails API to authenticate and login users

Mindless Meals - Github: http://bit.ly/2Rfy39v | Demo: http://bit.ly/2RGvuMG A single-page web application built with a **Javascript** front-end and a **Rails API** backend that allows users to quickly view a recipe to cook based on an ingredient in their refrigerator.

- Designed schema and integrated PostgreSQL database with my API to maintain data integrity
- Used AJAX to POST and GET data from Rails API to improve user experience
- Incorporated fast_jsonapi gem to return serialized JSON data from API quickly and reliably
- Organized Javascript code into multiple components and reusable functions to simplify debugging
- Styled using custom **CSS** to achieve a consistent design

Rachel Williams

Habit Tracker - Github: http://bit.ly/36inG9a | Demo: http://bit.ly/2RbJG13 A web application built with **Ruby on Rails** and **HTML** which allows users to create goals for habits they would like to change in their life and track their completion.

- Included the **omniauth** and omniauth-facebook gems to authenticate users with Facebook
- Encrypted passwords using **bcrypt** gem to ensure data was secure
- Used strong parameters to protect from unexpected request params
- Utilized **Rails** validations to ensure only valid data was persisted to the database
- Applied **Bootstrap** to front-end for a simple yet attractive design

Beat Roaster - Github: http://bit.ly/3avT07m | Demo: http://bit.ly/2RbpXyi A *Sinatra* and *Ruby* application where users can read and write reviews for their favorite music albums.

- Exercised full CRUD operations to add, view, edit and delete album review data using **ActiveRecord**
- Used **Sqlite3** database for simple querying and data integrity
- Utilized rack-flash3 gem to display flash messages for error handling

EDUCATION

Software Engineering Program

Apr 2019 - Jan 2020

Flatiron School

B.S. Biological Sciences

Sept 2008 — Jun 2012

University of California, Davis

WORK EXPERIENCE

Nohla Therapeutics

Apr 2018 - Jan 2019

Clinical Manufacturing Specialist

- Our team produced 100% of the required product for our clinical trial on time
- Reviewed and tracked batch records to ensure timely release for all lots
- Point of contact for Quality Assurance to resolve lot disposition issues and communicate to team

Genentech Inc.

Apr 2014 — Apr 2018

Senior BioProcess Technician

- Promoted from BioProcess Technician (April 2014 June 2016)
- Effectively communicated with internal departments to troubleshoot, document, and resolve issues during production using software and documents such as Microsoft Visio, P&ID, and PI
- Selected to join the Change Management Team Red-lined SOPs and automation documents with process improvements and vetted changes with internal departments
- White belt certification acquired in 2016 Training led by the Operational Excellence department to utilize multiple root cause analysis tools to reduce human error and increase process efficiency
- Selected to be a primary member of the Changeover Team Responsibilities included leading my shift in changeover activities and coordinating department specific activities with internal and external groups to avoid equipment conflicts

Rachel Williams